Sabbir Ahmed

Email: sabbirahmed@iut-dhaka.edu | **Phone:** (880) 1754221481 **Google Scholar:** https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=I_Dk4ZoAAAAJ

About Me

I am an Assistant Professor in the Dept of CSE at Islamic University of Technology (IUT). I am in the Computer Vision lab, advised by Prof. Hasanul Kabir. Before that, I received a M.Sc. and B.Sc. (Gold medalist) from IUT respectively in the year 2022 and 2017. My current research is in improving few-shot learning algorithms for image classification tasks. Besides, I've worked with different applications of deep learning in the field of computer vision such as leaf disease classification, gait analysis, traffic sign detection, handwritten digit recognition, etc.

Education

· M.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering

2018 - 2021

Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Islamic University of Technology

CGPA: 4.00/4.00

Thesis: Classification of Plant Disease from Leaf images using Few-shot Learning *Supervisor:* Dr. Md. Hasanul Kabir, Professor, IUT

· B.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering

2014 - 2017

Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Islamic University of Technology

CGPA: 3.93/4.00 (First Class First - IUT Gold Medalist)

Thesis: Image Classification using Deep Learning and Convolutional Neural Network

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Hasanul Kabir, Professor, IUT

• Higher Secondary School Certificate (HSC)

2011 - 2012

Chittagong College *GPA:* 5.00/5.00

Experience

· Assistant Professor

September 2022 - Present

Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Islamic University of Technology

Courses conducted: Pattern Recognition, Data Structures, Algorithms, Linear Algebra, Digital Logic Design, Web Programming

Other responsibilities: Moderator-IUT Computer Society (IUTCS), Advisor-IUT Programming Community (IUTPC), Online exam coordination, Course load distribution, Student advisor for Third year.

• **Lecturer** 2018 - August 2022

Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Islamic University of Technology

• Intern November 2016

XeonBD, Bangladesh

Responsibilities: WordPress based projects

Publications

Journal

- Ahmed, S., Hasan, M., Ahmed, T., Sony, R. K., & Kabir, M. (2022). Less is More: Lighter and Faster Deep Neural Architecture for Tomato Leaf Disease Classification. *IEEE Access*. doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2022.3187203.
- Alanezi, M. A., Shahriar, M. S., Hasan, M. B., **Ahmed, S.**, Sha'aban, Y. A., & Bouchekara, H. R. (2022) Livestock Management with Unmanned Aerial Vehicles: A Review. *IEEE Access*. doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2022.3168295

Conference

 Yasmeen, A., Rahman, F. I., Ahmed, S., & Kabir, M. H. (2021, August). CSVC-Net: Code-Switched Voice Command Classification using Deep CNN-LSTM Network. In 2021 Joint 10th International Conference on Informatics, Electronics & Vision (ICIEV) and 2021 5th International Conference on Imaging, Vision & Pattern Recognition (icIVPR) (pp. 1-8). IEEE. doi: 10.1109/ICIEVicIVPR52578.2021.9564183. • Khatun, A., Shahriar, M. S., Hasan, M. H., Das, K., **Ahmed, S.**, & Islam, M. S. (2021, August). A Systematic Review on the Chronological Development of Bangla Sign Language Recognition Systems. In 2021 Joint 10th International Conference on Informatics, Electronics & Vision (ICIEV) and 2021 5th International Conference on Imaging, Vision & Pattern Recognition (icIVPR) (pp. 1-9). IEEE. doi: 10.1109/ICIEVicIVPR52578.2021.9564157

Under Review

Ashikur Rahman, A. B. M., Bakhtiar Hasan, M., Ahmed, S., Ahmed, T., Hamjajul Ashmafee, M., Ridwan Kabir, M., Hasanul Kabir, M. (2022). Two Decades of Bengali Handwritten Digit Recognition: A Survey. arXiv e-prints, arXiv-2206. preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.02234

Ongoing Research Projects

- · Leaf Disease Detection with Limited Data
 - Exploring different Deep Learning techniques to achieve high performance with limited amount of data.
- Pest Detection from images taken in the wild

Investigating the use of Deep learning techniques to effectively detect and segment pests from real-life images.

• Bangledeshi Traffic Sign Detection Benchmark

Curating a dataset containing traffic sign images representing real-life challenges from road of Bangladesh.

Training and Workshop

• Day long workshop on Outcome Based Education (OBE)

2021

Location: Gazipur, Bangladesh

Content: Detailed introduction of the terminologies regarding OBE to apply in course curriculum

· Software Quality Assurance for Web Development

2018

Islamic University of Technology

Location: Gazipur, Bangladesh

Content: Quality assurance and cyber security

Workshop: Project management and software testing tools

Other Experiences

• Reviewer 2022 - Present

Journal: IEEE Access

• Advisor 2018 - Present

IUT Programming Community (IUTPC), *IUT Computer Society (IUTCS)*

• Regional Mentor 2021 - Present

Smart Agro-Technology Innovation Youth Network (SAIYN)

Bangladesh Agricultural University (BAU)

Honors and Awards

• Best Presentation Award 2021

2021 10th International Conference on Informatics, Electronics & Vision (ICIEV)

• IUT Gold Medal 2018

Islamic University of Technology

• Champion 2016

App Development, AUW Tech Fest

• Runner Up

Project Showcasing, 8th National ICT Fest, ISlamic University of Technology

• OIC Full Free Scholarship

Islamic University of Technology

• 4 years Govt. Scholarship

Bangladesh Education Board for Higher Secondary Certificate

Extra-Curricular Activities	
Vice President IUT Computer Society (IUTCS)	2016 - 2017
 Organizer 9th National ICT Fest, IUT 	2017

References

• 2 years Govt. Scholarship

Dr. Md. Hasanul Kabir
 Professor
 Department of Computer Science and Engineering Islamic University of Technology
 Email: hasanul@iut-dhaka.edu

Bangladesh Education Board for Secondary School Certificate

• Dr. Abu Raihan Mostafa Kamal
Head of the Department
Department of Computer Science and Engineering
Islamic University of Technology
Email: raihan.kamal@iut-dhaka.edu

2012